### Ruslan Salyakhov

Tel.: +1 201 885-8752

Twenty years of professional programming experience with consistently increasing responsibilities in design and development of the commercial applications;

Ten years of experience in leading software development teams (up to 25 persons);

Eleven years of experience with emphasis on Big Data technologies;

Domain experience in investment banking, image recognition, digital media, and telco.

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

- Application design and programming in Java, Scala, Python, Shell;
- System architecture of real time streaming projects using Kafka and Apache Spark Streaming;
- Good Knowledge of Databases Cassandra, Hbase, ClickHouse;
- Data analysis using Jupyter Notebook and Apache Zeppelin;
- Experience with Docker and related patterns of deployment Kubernetes/OpenShift.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# Deutsche Bank, USA, 4/2019 – Present

Scala, Kafka, Spark Streaming, OpenShift, ClickHouse, RStudio, Tableau, Python, OpenCV.

# **Data Engineer**

Leading design and development of Intraday reporting systems using Big Data technology stack. The real time analysis of credit exposure, credit limit utilization, and monitoring of intraday activities. Implementation of batch jobs for historical analytics using Spark on Scala. Implemented helm charts for technical monitoring using Prometheus, Alertmanager, and Grafana to multiple environments in OpenShift cluster.

#### R&D

Implementation of automated visual tests for web application UI using OpenCV, SikuliX, Selenium, and Python.

# **Luxoft USA, USA,** 10/2016 – 3/2019

Scala, Python, Hadoop, Hive, Cloudera Impala, Spark, Kafka, Apache Solr, Apache Flume, Qlikview, Bash shell and Python scripts, Oracle PL/SQL.

### **Big Data Hadoop Architect**

**Projects** The Volcker Rule Reporting System, Secured Data Lake.

# Responsibilities

Onsite consulting, mentoring and expert assessment of Big Data projects;

Profiling data in HDFS: data formats, compression, size of the files end etc.

Review hardware resources utilization and optimization of resources allocation for efficient processing of data on clusters;

Data analysis using Zeppelin, Spark, and Hadoop command line utilities;

# **Luxoft Professional LLC, Russia,** 09/17/2012 – 10/21/2016

Java, Scala, Python, Hadoop, Spark, Kafka, Elasticsearch, Flume, Fluentd, Qlikview, Pentaho BI, Bash shell and Python scripts, Oracle, PL/SQL.

### **Lead Software Architect**

Managed development teams with growing responsibility for up to 25 developers. Code review and project documentation control;

Mentoring and expert assessment of Big Data projects;

People management (motivation, hiring, personal appraisal, improving employees' technical abilities).

### **IQMEN - Business Intelligence, Russia,** 4/2011 – 8/2012

Information and Analytical Technologies Java, Hadoop, PostgreSQL, GIT.

#### **Team Lead**

Advisor and mentor of architectural design, cluster configurations and performance tuning utilizing of Hadoop ecosystem for data processing and analysis; Analysis and arrange requirements.

# **CONTEXTWEB, Russia,** 1/2010 – 4/2011

Real-time contextual advertising solutions

Java, Apache Hadoop, Apache Hive, PIG, Apache HBase, Qlikview, Hadoop MapReduce.

## **Team Lead/Senior Java Developer**

Managing remote team; Performance tuning. Created the coder for in-house framework that encodes an output of MapReduce jobs to the QlikView's native format for a fast loading.

### MVK, Russia, 7/2008 – 10/2009

Visual search technologies.

Linux, Java, Berkeley DB, Apache Hadoop, JProfiler, JMeter.

### Team Lead/Senior Java Developer

VISUVI - Visual search engine, startup, the revolutionary visual search technology that allows searching similar images by content.

Odnoklassniki.ru, Russia, 8/2007 - 6/2008, Senior Java Developer NetCracker Technology, Russia, 1/2004 - 7/2007, Senior Java Developer ICL KMECS, Russia, 9/1999 - 1/2004, Software Developer

### **EDUCATION**

**Kazan State University** named after V.I. Ulyanov-Lenin, 1994-1999 Mathematician majoring in "Applied Mathematics".

### **CERTIFICATIONS**

Machine Learning - Coursera Course Certificate

https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/verify/KCXRC8S6AV7E

Functional Programming Principles in Scala

https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/verify/HB32YD75D54R

Coding for fun <a href="https://github.com/salvakhov">https://github.com/salvakhov</a>